Daniel Hale is a bona fide American hero
I don't say that lightly most of you
know that whistleblower's motivation is
irrelevant to be a whistleblower one
must only bring to light evidence of
waste fraud abuse illegality or threats
to the public health or Public Safety
but Daniel Hale made his Revelations
because it was the right thing to do he
felt moral and ethical outrage at what
he was seeing in his job as a drone
operator and he felt compelled to do
something about it
hail released documents that came to be
known as the Drone papers to the online
news Outlet the intercept and he spoke
out again later in an award-winning film
called national bird he said for example
that during one five-month period in
2012 nearly 90 percent of those people
killed in drone strikes were not the
intended targets but civilian bystanders
innocent people killed were classified
as enemies killed in action unless
proven otherwise
we're going to talk about this
outrageous case with our guest Ray
McGovern Ray is a former senior Cia
officer who served for 27 years he was
President George H.W Bush's morning
intelligence briefer and was the
recipient of the cia's intelligence
Commendation Medal which he returned in
protest Rey is now a noted activist and
is the co-founder of Veteran
intelligence Professionals for sanity
Ray welcome to the show
Ray you know Daniel Hale personally so
many whistleblowers come to
whistleblowing from different points of
view give us an overview of his case
Daniel Hale was just a guy doing a job
how did all that change
well he realized that there's a
gradation of values to your job
and the one that supersedes all the
others is the Oaths that we all take
uh to support and defend the
Constitution of the United States
against all enemies foreign and domestic
when he saw what we're doing with these
drones in these forever Wars his
conscience
his conscience prevailed okay and when
he saw that over a five-month period
this is really as clearly indicated in
the in the documents a 200 people were
killed with drones
ninety percent like nine zero percent
were civilians counted as military
casualties now if my arithmetic is
correct
uh 200 kills uh 180 of those civilians
now his conscience told him that he
needed to stop that whatever he could do
he'd stop it he knew and I know this
personally he knew the risk he was
taking he was going to take it anyway
he's the best tradition of
whistleblowers I mean
his far distant predecessor relative
even Nathaniel Hale remember I regret
that I only have one life to give for my
country wow you don't get any better
than that in other words he knew what he
was doing when he went into it like
Daniel Ellsberg
like Edward Snowden they fully expected
to have to spend the rest of their life
in jail for exposing something that
their oath to the Constitution and their
conscious dictated that they expose
now
not all of us are up to that
are you or John
but I wasn't maybe I could give you a
negative example of that by and by
during this interview
one of the things that has struck me
about Daniel Hale is how intelligent he
is he's an extraordinarily bright young
man his whistleblowing was calculated he
knew exactly what he was getting himself
into his Revelations were not an
accident my point here is that he made a
decision to put the stories of Untold
victims of the Drone program and the
futures of possible drone victims above
his own well-being do you see his
situation the same way he wasn't the
proverbial accidental whistleblower was
he no he was very deliberate and you
know watching our government
for example I remember very very
specifically that Dianne Feinstein who
is supposed to be uh the what they call
the the uh supervisory committee uh the
committee that looks at uh CIA and other
operations uh she was like sort of the
Overlook committee and when she
interviewed John Brennan sort of like
the Godfather in both senses of the word
of this drone program when he was about
to become head of Central Intelligence
she said Oh Mr Mr I wasn't uh let's see
it was it was tender like no no it was
Brenda okay look she said Mr Brennan
uh it's a wonderful program I'm told
that the number of Civilian casualties
are are in the single digits and
brother smile is yeah
a bunch of I mean but butcher Milwaukee
all right single digits well I've just
told you for one five month period uh
ten percent or Twenty eighty percent of
the people killed were actually
civilians so uh when uh Dan Hale looked
at that and saw that you know the the
intelligence uh committees were not
going to reveal what was going on he
decided to do it himself and it's to his
great credit that he did that despite
risking uh in prison imprisonment where
he is now so you don't get too many
people like that you Owen John Ellsberg
was another and I have to tell you it's
Snowden said specifically when he
arrived in Hong Kong he said I know the
CIA station is right down this Street
here and they're gonna I know they're
almost certainly going to get me uh but
I I'll do it anyway because I swore an
oath to the Constitution all right the
fourth amendment in the Constitution and
that's what I was trying to protect now
in the event
it was Julian Assange Sarah Harrison and
others who got him out of there and it
was incredibly Artful way that they got
him on that aeroflow plane that's
another story but he lived to tell the
tale and he's got a small family now two
little boys and a wife in Moscow he'd
like to be here in this country but he's
proud of what he did and we needed to
know what he did again Congress did not
act as it should have in prohibiting NSA
CIA and others from continuing to
violate the Fourth Amendment of the
Constitution of the United States when
Daniel Hale decided to make his
Revelations he went to the intercept
this was actually quite controversial
because many National Security
whistleblowers who have gone to the
intercept have found themselves to be
sent to trial and then on to prison NSA
whistleblower reality winner for example
went to The Intercept they exposed her
idea identity FBI whistleblower Terry
Albury went to the intercept and they
exposed his identity the two national
security journalists at The Intercept
Richard Esposito and Matthew Cole were
the journalists responsible for sending
me to prison the same thing that
happened to all of us happened to Daniel
Hale at The Intercept what is going on
there are they that unprofessional or
are they somehow connected to the
National Security establishment
well The Intercept has fallen on bad
times when you think how it was set up
and what it was out to do what has
happened well you know the proof is in
the pudding they were unwilling to
publish uh green Walls expose of the
Biden laptop story before the last
election wow they sat on it they uh they
wouldn't publish what Robert Greenwald
had he had a publish himself and he had
to leave The Intercept a institution
that he had himself co-founded
now from what I know and no one knows
everything about everything of these
cases that you just mentioned
my impression is that Daniel Hale
was convinced that he would be found out
and that he was willing to pay the price
unlike the others
uh there is circumstantial evidence that
he didn't take the rudimentary
precautions that prevent the what the
Soviets used to call the organs of State
security from finding out who you were
so the others I think were really
traceable to incompetence or Worse
Daniels uh I happen on enough about that
to indicate that he was willing to pay
the price and he's unwilling to hide for
the rest of his life so I'm not saying
it's on his own fault but he he knew
that going in and he acted in that way
so his case in my view was a little bit
different Daniel Hale at his sentencing
gave one of the most inspirational
speeches that I've ever heard in my life
in that statement that he made he said
and I quote I believe that it is wrong
to kill but it is especially wrong to
kill the defenseless I shared what was
necessary to dispel the lie that drone
Warfare keeps us safe that our lives are
worth more than theirs unquote he also
said that he had to kill a part of his
own conscience to do his job he also
paraphrased his ancestor Nathan Hale and
said I have but this one life to give in
the service of my country
these are incredibly powerful words Ray
at the same time the prosecutor in this
case said that Daniel did not provide a
public service he endangered soldiers
there is of course nothing at all to
indicate that this was the case give me
your thoughts on Daniel Hale's Legacy
what do you think that'll be
well that's what prosecutors do of
course they're not above twisting the
truth
I'm reminded of when uh Chelsea Manning
uh revealed the secrets on our Wars in
Iraq and Afghanistan the initial
complaint from the prosecutors and from
everybody else was that we are
endangering Source endangering sources
and methods and not only that but people
well guess what uh when the head of
defense department at the time Philip
lanium Robbie gate Robert Gates was
asked to substantiate that he came back
and told the head of the Senate arms
committee arms Services committee Levin
was his name he said well you know we've
looked into this and there's no evidence
that anyone was harmed by virtue of
these disclosures so they couldn't
substantiate that anyone so much was so
much a spat-upon in in reaction to these
truths coming out so that's always a
that's always a technique that the
prosecutors use uh you know
when you think about the people
that Dan Hale saw being killed or you
know Gathering chestnuts or gathering
grapes or whatever being killed uh who
are these people
well the powers that be the John
Brennan's of this world consider those
people
well with the term is used to call unto
mentioned
okay people that boo below the rest of
us mention okay
now when he talked about
his conscience uh you know my conscience
is also formed by what we Catholics call
the preferential option for the poor
and the British and the British might
get
and the Vatican made that explicitly
clear back in
1975 when they said here's what that
means here's what that means a
preferential option for the poor no one
quote no one is entitled to accumulate
still more or what he doesn't need
when others lack the rudimentary basics
of Life period end quote well the
Supreme indignity of course is being
deprived of life without due process and
that's what was happening to 90 percent
of those civilians in Afghanistan Iraq
under that Brennan regime do you
remember John I think it was uh every
Tuesday it was Tuesday or Thursday I
think it was Tuesday the John Brennan
bought a list to President Obama
and that list included the names of
people who would be uh who would be
obliterated by drones that particular
week okay and you know can you see it I
mean here's Obama said no John huh this
fellow Ali so-and-so uh
didn't you tell me that is a a wife of
five kids
uh yeah Mr President we found out that
he was having lunch with a suspect
terrorists in Lebanon so I take it you
think we get again and get them well
John you know
let's put him out let's put him at the
bottom of the list and and let's look at
that again next week let's let's kill
the other ten okay Chad oh yes sir Mr
President hello
give me a break
but that's the way it went down and no
one no one was held accountable the only
way we know all this stuff is for people
like Daniel Hale my hat's off to him
I want to ask you about people
considering becoming whistleblowers
especially in the National Security
Arena I get calls from people with some
frequency asking for advice I'm sure you
do too what do you tell people like
Daniel Hale who are struggling with a
decision to go public it's not a secret
that the entire weight of the US
government will fall on their heads if
they go public with their information
well I say if you're in Hawaii Fly East
what do I mean by that I mean Edward
Snowden had done his homework
he knew that he went
it went to the U.S or any points West
East for him whatever it was to the U.S
he couldn't escape being found out and
in prison so he went to Hong Kong that's
why he went to Hong Kong to release this
stuff to give it to journalists and have
a couple days before they found him he
fully expected to be found as I said
before so he was able to do this why
because he was smart enough doubts
outsmart the system so I'd say to a
whistleblower look at first you need to
you need to decide if you're willing to
to risk what might be in in store for
you and if you are well my I give you my
my unadulterated uh encouragement now uh
before you go and do this thing figure
out how best to do it and how most
securely to do it there are all kinds of
ways these days okay not only Wikileaks
but others so figure that out and go
ahead do it and don't be left with the
kind of conscience
that I have
when Daniel Hale was sentenced in the
notorious district court for the eastern
district of Virginia judge Liam O'Grady
shocked Everybody by giving him a
sentence of 45 months in prison but
judge O'Grady recommended that Daniel go
to a low security prison where he could
be treated for depression and addiction
issues the U.S Bureau of Prisons ignored
that recommendation and instead sent him
to the communications management unit of
the super max prison at Marion Illinois
this is one of the two most secure and
most dreaded prisons in the entire U.S
prison system Daniel is now incarcerated
with some of the most dangerous people
in the world including terrorists and
Mafia leaders what's the message that we
should all take from this it was the
same message that we're giving we're
trying to give with respect to Julian
Assange
we're gonna get you and we get you gonna
treat you brutally we're going to get
you we're going to put you in prison so
don't do don't do what you might be
tempted to do what your conscience tells
you you should do okay it's it's that
brutal and those people are running
running and not that the judges for
God's sake the prison people the what we
call the Deep State all those three
letter agencies that have purview over
our government to include over our
president I have to tell you uh look at
what's happening in Ukraine so you know
it's it's really a a a tough situation
and that's precisely now January I
visited you in prison are you able not
to end up in these really really beds
bad prisons but you know I just finished
with this thought about prisons it was
Dostoevsky
who said you know if you want to measure
the level of of civilization of a given
country
go visit its prisons
we wouldn't shape up very well under
those circumstances
Daniel will be released from prison
raised sometime in early 2024. what can
he expect when he gets out certainly the
government will make his post-prison
life difficult they do that to all of us
what do you think awaits Daniel Hale
well I think he'll feel the same way you
did John and the others who have have
done their time like Chelsea Manning uh
Daniel Hill will be able to get the uh
the the
Oscar so to speak we call it the
candlestick holder for spreading light
and dark places of the Sam Adams
Association the same Sam Adams we'll be
giving him that in person and he will be
welcomed by those of us who know the
hardships that he will have endured and
who admire his courage in facing into
that even though he knew what the risks
were and told the truth anyway so there
will be a community you know you just
say I'm thinking John well you went away
to prison there was a mammoth ball a big
celebration on the top of one of the
fanciest hotels in Washington and we all
said goodbye John we'll see you later
and when you came back we welcomed you
so you know a lot of people a lot of
people still admire a courage and a
feeling of Integrity there'll be those
people to to welcome Daniel Hale as he
gets out of these ridiculous situations
in prison
veteran intelligence Professionals for
sanity the group that you co-founded
that's made up of retired officials from
the CIA FBI NSA the military and the
British MI5 and MI6 recently gave Daniel
Hale its Sam Adams award for integrity
and intelligence tell us about the award
and about why it was so important to
honor Daniel well there's no better
prize for someone he has a really good
predecessors in having that award
Colleen Rally from the FBI was the first
one 20 years ago okay 2002 we all know
what was happening then she warned about
it at other recipients have been uh
Julian Assange
um
okay
Manning uh many really courageous folks
so so Daniel is in this Heritage line of
uh 20 people he being the 20th have
stood up to the government and said look
our primary osis the Constitution you
are violating it so we're gonna we're
gonna expose what goes on here
um now Sam Adams already told you uh was
a person who was extremely bright and
had the right answers uh what happened
to him well he was shuns he was shunned
by the agency leadership uh Sam had a
lot of guts he went to the IG the
Inspector General and said I want I want
to uh do a complaint on Richard Helms
who happens to be the head of the CIA
because he's lying about Vietnam because
you can figure out how far he got with
that but finally uh he got his story out
and guess what Westmoreland the general
sued him sued him and CBS that did a
90-minute 60-minute segment on the
falsification of evidence on Vietnam and
guess what guess who won uh voice Mullen
had a withdraw from the suit because
people coming out of the woodwork saying
yeah Sam had the guts to say it right we
were repressed by a spoiling we were in
the Army we couldn't we couldn't resist
we needed to get promoted Sam did the
right thing so the whole thing uh you
know redounded to Sam's benefit
unfortunately Sam died early in 50 at 53
years old from an unexpected heart
attack I suspect that the whole thing
was wearing on him and he was unable to
enjoy uh basking in the in the glory of
what he actually did that's not going to
happen everybody so don't let that beard
return